Finding Aid for the Collection of Turkish Manuscripts LSC.0896
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Title (Romanized): Niyazü'l-müznibin Title (English): Needment of the guilty Alternative titles: ???? ????????, Niyaz al-mudhnibin, Date: 1844; Manuscript number: 101; 186 leaves: paper; 242 x 170 mm. bound to 242 x 177 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded black an
  Islam: work on religious requirements in rhyming Turkish couplets. Author had begun the work (9a) during the reign of Murad III (r. 1574-1595). Written with the help of a certain Abdülgaffar b. Mustafa b. Ilyas (185b).
- Title (Romanized): Tuhfetü'l-mülûk Title (English): The gift of kings Alternative titles: ???? ??????, Date: 1786 March; Manuscript number: 102; 96 leaves: paper; 248 x 170 mm. bound to 246 x 175 mm.; Layout: 25 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Burgundy leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 33)
  Turkish treatise on the arts of versification. Original was composed in April of 1653 (96a)
- Title (Romanized): Sifaü'l-mümin Title (English): The cure of the faithful Alternative titles: ???? ??????, Date: 1831; Manuscript number: 103; 172 leaves: paper; 240 x 171 mm. bound to 238 x 174 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, inlaid, with gilt edges, and orange paste-downs; fore-edge flap torn off and laid in. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 33)
  Treatise in Turkish on the Koran and the tenets of faith, dedicated to Sultan Mehmet IV (r. 1648-87)
- Title (Romanized): Tenkih-i tevârîh-i mülûk Title (English): A summary of the histories of kings Alternative titles: ????? ?????? ????, Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 104; 206 leaves: paper; 230 x 140 mm. bound to 236 x 155 mm.; Layout: 27 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Green marble paper on red leather, with gilt spine, and blue marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 34)
- Title (Romanized): Nihayetü'l-elbab tercüme-i hulâsatü'l-hesap Title (English): The finite point of understanding translating the summary of arithmetic Alternative titles: ????? ?????? ????? ???? ??????, Date: 1832 March; Manuscript number: 105; 135 leaves: paper; 240 x 154 mm. bound to 238 x 153 mm.; Layout: 25 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Variegated marble paper on red leather, with fore-edge flap, and yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; illustrations and formulae in red in the margins. (Box 34)
  The author actually calls himself not Kuyucakli but Kuyucaklizade Mehmet Âtif, but the Library Of Congress record for this author lists the dates 1850-1898, i.e. before the composition of the manuscript.
  A treatise on mathematics, being a translation of another work by the Safavid scholar Baha' al-Din Amili (1547-1621). The present manuscript is dedicated to the Ottoman Sultan Mahmud II (r. 1808-1839).
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i es-sittinü'l-câmi li-letaifi'l-besatin] Title (English): [The translation of collected sixty of the pleasures of gardens], Date: 1666 January; Manuscript number: 106; 229 leaves: paper; 235 x 132 mm. bound to 235 x 147 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Purple cloth on boards with brown leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; at least one leaf missing from the beginning; title garbled in manuscript; insect damage. (Box 34)
  A Turkish translation of a Persian commentary on the Koranic chapter on the prophet Joseph, the original being entitled al-sittin al-jamí li-la?a'if al- basatin and written by A?mad b. Mu?ammad ?usi (15th century). The Turkish text was composed in 1623 (229b) during the brief second reign of the Ottoman Sultan Mustafa (i.e. 1622-23) (1a).
- Title (Romanized): [missing from box], Manuscript number: 107; Layout: Script: Decoration: Binding: Additional description: (Box 34)
- Title (Romanized): Hadikatü's-süedâ Uniform title: Hadikatü's-sü'eda Title (English): Garden of the blessed folks Alternative titles: ????? ??????, Date: [15--]?; Manuscript number: 108; 265 leaves: paper; 245 x 161 mm. bound to 242 x 160 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded black leather, blind-stamped, with faded marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red and blue borders. (Box 34)
  Fuzulî's account of the martyrdom of the third Shiite imam ?usayn ibn Ali. The text is mainly a translation of the Persian-language Raw?at al- shuhada' by the Timurid author ?usayn Vaiz? Kashifi (d. 1504 or 5.)
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i serh-i dübeyt-i Câmi li-Hoca Nes'et] Uniform title: Tercüme-i serhi dübeyt-i molla Cami Title (English): [Translation of the commentary of the quartet of Jami by Hoca Nes'et], Date: 1851; Manuscript number: 109; 26 leaves: paper; 240 x 166 mm. bound to 235 x 164 mm.; Layout: 25 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Green and blue marble paper on boards, with brown leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; water damage; leaves separated. (Box 34)
  A commentary of Nes'et on the writing of the Sufi poet Jami (d. 1492). Copy of a manuscript dated 1846, during the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Abdülmecid.
- Title (Romanized): [Risale-i tasavvuf] Title (English): [Treatise on Sufism], Date: 1856; Manuscript number: 110; 25 leaves: paper; 240 x 148 mm. bound to 238 x 149 mm.; Layout: 23 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Faded green marble paper on boards, with brown leather stripe over spine, and yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; leaves separated. (Box 34)
  Author also known as Ali Aziz Efendi of Crete
  Treatise on Sufism, written in order to dispel misinformation.
- Title (Romanized): Tahmis-i kaside-i bürde Uniform title: Tahmis-i kaside-i bürde Title (English): Five-folding the poem known as burdah Alternative titles: ????? ????? ????, Tahmis-i kaside-i bür'e, Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 111; 24 leaves: paper; 245 x 168 mm. bound to 247 x 173 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Faux brown Morocco. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 34)
  Additions to a poem originally composed by Sharaf al-Din Mu?ammad Bu?iri (1213?-1296?) in Arabic about the qualities of the prophet Mu?ammad. The manuscript contains a shorter similar poetic exercise on the final two leaves.
- Title (Romanized): [Hikâyat-i e'imme-i isna 'asere] Title (English): [Tales of the twelve imams], Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 112; 177 leaves: paper; 233 x 147 mm. bound to 148 x 229 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Soft brown leather. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, few marked words in red; leaves missing from beginning and end; bottom edge title. (Box 34)
  Tales about the lives of the twelve Shiite imams.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i] Maariçü'n-nübüvve Uniform title: Maariç ün-nübüvve Title (English): [The translation of] ascensions of prophet-hood Alternative titles: ????? ??????, Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 113; 387 leaves: paper; 202 x 133 mm. bound to 201 x 144 mm.; Layout: 26 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Soft black leather, blind-stamped; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; leaves separated. (Box 35)
  Life-stories of prophets from Adam forward culminating with the life of Mu?ammad. Apparently a translation of a Persian text by Múin al-Din Farahi, d. 1501 or 2.
- Title (Romanized): [Hamzanâme] Title (English): [The book of ?amzah] Alternative titles: Romance of Amir ?amza, Dastan-i Amir Hamzah, Qissah-'i Hamzah, Hamzah'namah, Date: 1738; Manuscript number: 114; 209 leaves: paper; 207 x 148 mm. bound to 206 x 144 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Soft black leather; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink; frayed; leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 35)
  See DP reference below.
  This is a Turkish translation of the popular story of ?amzah ibn Abd al-Mu??alib (d. 625) the uncle of the prophet Mu?ammad.
- Title (Romanized): Hulviyat Title (English): Sweet things Alternative titles: ?ulwiyat-i shahi fi al-furu {in Kâtip Çelebi Kashf al-?unun}? ??????, Date: 1818 March; Manuscript number: 115; 389 leaves: paper; 203 x 143 mm. bound to 201 x 140 mm.; Layout: 26 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q and Naskh. Binding: Brown canvass on boards with red leather around the edges; fore-edge flap separated and laid in. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; marginalia; notes tipped and laid in. (Box 35)
  The author of this book is better known to history as Ismail Isfendiyaroglu, brother-in-law of the Ottoman Sultan Mehmed II who conquered Constantinople in 1453. Ismail wrote this book on religious precepts after the sultan removed him from the rule of the city of Sinop on the Black Sea coast
  It treats religious practices and doctrine such as ablution, prayer, mosques, and religious holidays. Translated from various sources for the benefit of "those who do not know Arabic and Persian". Author's name contains two other words which, transliterated by Arabic standard, read "Yaman Jandar" (the second word being Çandarl? in Turkish). The original dates to the early fifteenth-century (DP reference below).
- Title (Romanized): [Serh-i] Bostan Uniform title: Sudi serh-i Bostan Title (English): [Commentary on the] Orchard, Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 116; 432 leaves: paper; 203 x 130 mm. bound to 202 x 130 mm.; Layout: 23 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Faux orange Morocco with burgundy stripe over spine, and flower design paste-downs; fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; insect damage. (Box 35)
  Kâtip Çelebi mentions four commentators in his Kashf al- ?unun, but considers Sudi's best of them all, suggesting perhaps greater popularity and making the existence of numerous manuscripts more likely. Also important is the fact that from 139b, marginalia in red ink identifies quotations from Sem'i and Sururi, the other two commentators, who slightly predated Sudi--suggesting that the present commentary has taken material from the commentary of the former two, and is therefore not them but rather a third: i.e. Sudi's.
  A commentary on the Persian Bustan of Sádi, undertaken to facilitate the task of those who set out to learn Persian, presumably by memorizing or studying the original.
- Title (Romanized): Zeyl-i siyer-i nebevi Uniform title: Zeyl-i Nâbi Title (English): Continuation of the prophetic biographies Alternative titles: ??? ??? ????, Date: 1849; Manuscript number: 117; 329 leaves: paper; 216 x 152 mm. bound to 214 x 152 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faux orange Morocco with burgundy stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; marginalia. (Box 36)
  This is Nabi's continuation of an earlier biography of the prophet Mu?ammad entitled Dürretü't-taç and written by Veysî (1561- 1628).
- Title (English): [Tenets and doctrines of Islam], Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 118; 441 leaves: paper; 217 x 155 mm. bound to 218 x 1572 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Purple paper on boards with black cloth on spine; damaged. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; water damage. (Box 36)
  Translation and commentary of an Arabic text on the tenets and doctrines of Islam, drawing heavily on hadith, into Turkish. First and last leaves are glued to the cover and thus hide the identity and date of the manuscript.
- Title (Romanized): Saadet-name Title (English): Book of felicity Alternative titles: ????? ????, Date: Before 1624; Manuscript number: 119; 181 leaves: paper; 208 x 149 mm. bound to 209 x 150 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; leaves missing from the end. (Box 36)
  Author also known as Câmî-i M?srî and Gelibolulu Ali Ahmet (See the article "Hüseyn Vaiz Kâsifi" in Türkiye Diyanet Vakf? Islâm ansiklopedisi).
  The manuscript seems to be an abridgement (see 1b) of Câmî's translation of Rawzat al-al-shuhada' by ?usayn Vai? Kashifi (d. 1504 or 5) covering the death of the third Shiite Imam ?usayn ibn Ali.
- Title (Romanized): Vikayetü'r-rivaye fi mesaili'l-hidaye Title (English): The preserving of narratives regarding the issues of guidance Alternative titles: ????? ??????? ?? ????? ???????, Tercüme-i vikaye fi'l-fikh el-serif, Date: 1690 June; Manuscript number: 120; 333 leaves: paper; 216 x 152 mm. bound to 214 x 152 mm.; Layout: 23 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded black or burgundy leather with fore-edge flap, and marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, green, or blue, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 36)
  The identity of the author inferred from Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. I: 135, as well as Kâtip Çelebi's Kashf al-?unun, under the original title, where there is also noted a commentary in Turkish by Arap Çelebi (Semsettin ahmet b. Hamza; d. 1543 or 4)
  Translation into Turkish of an Arabic original composed by the fourteenth century al-Ma?bubi, itself being an epitome of a work by al-Marghinani (d. 1196 or 7).
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i] Vefayatü'l-âyan Uniform title: Tercüme-yi Vefayat ül-âyan li-bin Khallikan Title (English): The translation of the Obituaries of notables Alternative titles: ????? ??????, Wafayat al-áyan., Date: 1715 April; Manuscript number: 121; 260 leaves: paper; 214 x 132 mm. bound to 212 x 136 mm.; Layout: 23 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather, inlaid, with fore-edge flap, and pink paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 37)
  This is a Turkish translation of Ibn Khallikan's (1211-1282) biography of Muslim notables. The translation was undertaken in 1676 and was dedicated to a vizier named Mustafa Pasa which must be Merzifonlu Kara Mustafa Pasa who served as vizier from 167683.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i Harîdet'ül-acayip ve feridet'ül-garaib]? Title (English): [The translation of the Untouched among the wonders and the Unique among the curiosities], Date: [16--]; Manuscript number: 122; 246 leaves: paper; 215 x 141 mm. bound to 217 x 145 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; leaves missing after leaf 1, and at the end. (Box 37)
  A Turkish text about the wonders of the world. The author refers to himself specifically as the translator. On leaf 2a, there is poem written for a certain Osman Pasa. A noted penciled in the margins, in a late 19th/early 20th century hand, equates this person with Osman b. Iskender Pasa. The identification of the title arises from this equation and its correspondence with the relative information in Kâtip Çelebi's Kashf al-?unun.
- Title (Romanized): Enis'ül-ârifîn Title (English): Companion of the knowers Alternative titles: ???? ????????, Date: 1636; Manuscript number: 123; 172 leaves: paper; 207 x 148 mm. bound to 205 x 148 mm.; Layout: Average 19 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Faded discolored paper on boards and brown leather. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; water damage. (Box 37)
  Possibly Pir Mehmet bin Evrenos bin Nureddin Zaifî, d. 1559 (?)
  A Turkish translation of the ethical and political treatise of ?usayn Vai? Kashifi (d. 1504 or 5.) entitled Akhlaq-i Mu?sini, completed (according to Kâtip Çelebi) in 1566. The manuscript contains 3 other titles.
- Title (Romanized): en-Nazmü'l-mübin fi'l-ayati'l-erbain Uniform title: En-Nazm ül-mübin fi 'l-ayat il-erbain; ve, Ahsen ül-hadis fi 'l-ahadis il-erbain Title (English): The manifest order in the forty [Koranic] verses Alternative titles: ????? ?????? ?? ????? ???????, Date: 1779 October; Manuscript number: 124; 321 leaves: paper; 212 x 137 mm. bound to 212 x 137 mm.; Layout: 25 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap, and pink-and-white paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 37)
  A treatise on a select number of Koranic verses and their exegetical interpretation. The author had appended another treatise of his called Ahsenü'l-hadis fi'l-ahadis il-erbain as the preface to the main title.
- Title (Romanized): Siret[ü'n-nebi] Title (English): The life [of the prophet] Alternative titles: [???? [?????, Date: 1762 August; Manuscript number: 125; 367 leaves: paper; 214 x 160 mm. bound to 209 x 161 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather with leather stripe over spine; torn and frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; enclosed in red borders. (Box 37)
  The story of life of the prophet Mu?ammad in Turkish rhyming couplets.
- Title (Romanized): [Kitap-i Siretü'n-nebi] Title (English): [The book of the life of the prophet], Date: 1794 May; Manuscript number: 126; 157 leaves: paper; 306 x 103 mm. bound to 311 x 110 mm.; Layout: 29 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Black canvass on boards. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, heading in red; 1b & 2a enclosed in red borders. (Box 38)
  The story of life of the prophet Mu?ammad in Turkish rhyming couplets (different from mss. 125 above).
- Title (Romanized): Muhammediye Uniform title: Muhammediye Title (English): [The book] of Muhammad Alternative titles: ??????? ????????, Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 127; 280 leaves: paper; 281 x 180 mm. bound to 280 x 182 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black canvass on boards. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; final leaf separating. (Box 38)
  Islam: doctrine and belief regarding the world, God, prophets, angels, signs of judgment day, etc. A verse translation into Turkish of the author's Magharib al-zaman, translated also by his brother into Turkish prose (Envar ül-âsikîn). The verse translation was completed in August 1449.
- Title (Romanized): Muhammediye Uniform title: Muhammediye Title (English): [The book] of Muhammad Alternative titles: ??????? ????????, Date: 1647 June; Manuscript number: 128; 275 leaves: paper; 278 x 180 mm. bound to 280 x 180 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather; fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 39)
- Title (Romanized): Muhammediye Uniform title: Muhammediye Title (English): [The book] of Muhammad Alternative titles: ??????? ????????, Date: 1796 November; Manuscript number: 129; 236 leaves: paper; 327 x 224 mm. bound to 227 x 225 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather; blind-stamped; fore-edge flap; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; water damage; leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 39)
- Title (Romanized): Maariçü'n-nübüvve Uniform title: Maariç ün-nübüvve Title (English): The ascensions of prophet-hood Alternative titles: ????? ??????, Date: 1724; Manuscript number: 130; 375 leaves: paper; 313 x 197 mm. bound to 317 x 205 mm.; Layout: 29 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather; blind-stamped; fore-edge flap; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some water damage. (Box 40)
  Stories of the life of the prophet Mu?ammad, emphasizing his ascension to heaven. The text is based on Múin al-Din Farahi's Máarif al-nubuwwah fi madarij al-futuwwah. As Kâtip Çeleb has noted, the present title is different from a first (and earlier) Turkish translation of this text by Mustafa Çelebi Celâlzade.
- Title (Romanized): Fazilet-nâme Uniform title: Fazilet-nâme Title (English): The book of virtue Alternative titles: ????? ????, Date: [17--]; Manuscript number: 131; 278 leaves: paper; 266 x 191 mm. bound to 275 x 199 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; some marginalia in pencil. (Box 40)
  A long poem in rhyme couplets about the prophet Mu?ammad and his descendants, the Shiite imams.
- Title (Romanized): Hâzâ Kitap-i nakl-i Hüseyn evlat-i Ali der vasf-i Kerbelâ Title (English): This book is the story of ?usayn child of Ali in the description of Karbala Alternative titles: ??? ???? ???? ???? ??? ?? ??? ????, Maktel-i Hüseyni, Date: no date; Manuscript number: 132; 117 leaves: paper; 281 x 188 mm. bound to 275 x 199 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap; badly torn and frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; some water damage. (Box 40)
  A popular account of the martyrdom of the third Shiite imam ?usayn ibn Ali.
- Title (Romanized): Mersiye der hakk-i Seyyidü's-süheda Title (English): Elegy in honor of the Lord of martyrs Alternative titles: ????? ?? ?? ??? ???????, Date: [19--]; Manuscript number: 133; 6 leaves: paper; 243 x 148 mm. bound to 247 x 151 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faux brown Morocco. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink. (Box 41)
  A short elegy in verse on the martyrdom of the third Shiite imam ?usayn ibn Ali.
- Title (Romanized): Hâzâ Kitap maktel-i imam Hüseyn Title (English): This book is the death account of imam ?usayn Alternative titles: ??? ???? ???? ???? ????, Date: 1883 March; Manuscript number: 134; 42 leaves: paper; 245 x 180 mm. bound to 238 x 192 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh/Riqa. Binding: Black leather blind-stamped. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink; stained. (Box 41)
  A versified account of the martyrdom of the third Shiite imam ?usayn ibn Ali. The author has written that he had composed it "in Kastamonu the seat of the throne" and gives the date 1361 (42a).
- Title (Romanized): Serefü'l-insan Title (English): The nobility of man Alternative titles: ??? ??????, Date: 1606 March; Manuscript number: 135; 203 leaves: paper; 215 x 149 mm. bound to 222 x 157 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black Morocco with leather over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 41)
  A fabled exchange between animals and men, translated from the treatise called Ikhwan al-?afa' into Turkish for Sultan Süleyman the magnificent.